<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>Ivan Bogachev</title>
<description>Personal blog. A mix of programming and behavioral psychology with a touch of philosophy.</description>
<link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://sfi0zy.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"
type="application/rss+xml"/>
<pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 12:39:03 GMT</pubDate>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 12:39:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
    <title>Request-Response</title>
    <description><p>Dancing girl? Fire! Puppy? Aww! Shooting? Angry! Request? Response! Honeymoon? Heart! Request? Response! Lady in a club? Devil! Request? Response. System? System. Request? Response. Interlinked? Interlinked. Request? Response. Interlinked. Interlinked. We're done. You can pick up your snack.</p><p>Have you heard about Pavlov's dog and all those experiments around classical conditioning? These days we exploit all of that knowledge to make you repeat actions on social media platforms and related services. You're like a test dog now.</p><p>We train armies of consumers to produce reactions from curated lists to stimuli from other lists. We write software that replaces supervisors in those experiments and rings the "reward bell" for you. Lazy consumption (11 + 14) turns into a well-structured race with forced rules and goals that you have to achieve while consuming to get more stuff to consume.</p><p>These patterns of behavior are not designed to work in that environment. Things can get sideways really fast. You may not want to stop consuming, but now you need additional actions to handle the pressure. It's easy to accidentally stack a <a href='/post/unresolvable-conflict'>set of incompatible patterns</a> and get a full house of mental problems.</p><p>On top of that, overstimulation with information is one of the standard DoS attacks. Your CPU and memory are 100% loaded, but you use only a fraction of that computing power for your real-life tasks. Your system loses its efficiency. The hardware is functional, but it takes ages to process any complex material.</p><p>This is a disaster for iPad kids. It greatly slows down their development. Their <a href='/post/internal-world'>internal worlds</a> are smaller than expected. Behavior doesn't match their age. Lack of basic skills. No goals. No values to fight for. Just a void in their hearts and a list of standardized reactions to choose from.</p><p>It's difficult to revert conditioning. We don't have a Ctrl+Z shortcut in our brains. If you want to get out, stop scrolling and buying, and get resources to do other things, you'll have to do that the hard way, like a proper junkie.</p><p>It may look like future generations are doomed, but is that true? I mean, only 2 out of 16 patterns of behavior of class I can be deeply affected. They become prevalent in developed countries, but they're not the only ones. We have other options as well.</p><p>This whole "kids can't read" situation is a part of consumer culture. We didn't inherit any highly regulated races for the title of the best consumer of the year from nature. We created them as sets of collective rules with some contradictions. Will you force your kids to follow them or not is totally up to you.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/request-response</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/request-response</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>psychology</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Bait-therapy</title>
    <description><p>When we deal with emotions, or, better to say, with different states of the system, we inevitably understand that some of them are <a href='/post/fear'>temporary by design</a>. They can't last.</p><p>This opens a door into a field of interventions that we may call bait-therapies. We incite the system, trigger some active response, and wait until it ends. After that, there is a gap, a period of time when the same response can't be reactivated.</p><p>That gap can be abused in various ways. You let a person cry a river, until one can't cry no more, and then you talk. Or you make a ritual doll that represents somebody, cut its eyes, rip its head off, and throw it into a fire. Yes, it brings peace.</p><p>The person gets into a position where cold-blooded logic is the only thing that works, because everything else is either recharging or waiting for other kinds of maintenance. This is when you may suggest something and make a discussion.</p><p>Some psychological approaches, like gestalt-therapy or art-therapy, use this trick when <a href='/post/trauma'>working with traumas</a>. You allow patients to live within a simulation, talk to an empty chair or draw an imaginary world, and experience various extreme states of their psyche. After that, they get a relief of sorts and learn something. We may see that as a successful session.</p><p>However, this trick doesn't solve any problems. It just allows you to exaggerate a part of your patterns of behavior without interacting with real everyday environments. It's not enough.</p><p>The pattern repeats. It's a loop. Fish bites the same bait again and again. You can stay in therapy for years with zero progress, just replaying the same situation over and over.</p><p>If you want to get out, you have to do stuff. Not just live through your emotions. It's a meaningless goal. They'll get back at the next iteration of the loop anyway.</p><p>Break a pattern. Choose another one. Get a new set of values. Build a new life. The bait will become irrelevant at some point. You don't hide or deny it. No. You just don't get triggered anymore. You have other priorities now.</p><p>This exit from therapy should be obvious, and yet I see tons of examples where people don't get there. Changes that they get from their therapy don't last. They get back with a new disturbing story that looks almost like the one before.</p><p>Your job as a therapist isn't baiting. Make sure that your client is changing and not just getting that temporary peace of mind. That apparent stability is a bait for you.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/bait-therapy</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/bait-therapy</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>psychology</category>
        <category>emotions</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Good, bad, traditional</title>
    <description><p>As intelligent beings, we create lots of rules to guide our behavior. We have to stick to the standard set of patterns to avoid <a href='/post/unresolvable-conflict'>unresolvable logical conflicts</a>, but we're free to make local choices and fine-tune the patterns to our taste.</p><p>We're smart enough to create rules with a <a href='/post/pathfinders'>purpose</a>. They're not just rules for the sake of rules. We create them to achieve something. We don't like spending our precious resources on following rules that don't lead to any rewards at all, do we?</p><p>Is some rule a good one or a bad one? Look at your goals. If the rule helps you to achieve them, then it's a good one. If it doesn't, then it's a bad one. No need to complicate this.</p><p>In some cases, we can compare resources required to achieve our goals in different scenarios and find the best rule, the most efficient among the good ones.</p><p>Everything looks well-organized at first, but then we start to forget things. How many rules in the core of our society still have clear purposes? How many rules lost them completely?</p><p>A significant amount of the collective rules are in use not because they actually lead us to something valuable. People follow them to get formal appreciation or avoid condemnation from their ancestors who have the same motivations to follow them. These aren't your standard rules anymore, but "traditions".</p><p>They don't have any purpose. It's quite the opposite. They emerge when we forget our initial goals. We repeat actions as usual, like there is some meaning behind them... Was. There was a meaning. We lost it, actually. But there was one. All our rules are important. Don't ask stupid questions!</p><p>Goal-oriented rules get outdated, but traditions are timeless, and, as any other rules that we follow for a while, they become a part of who we are. They shape family things, subcultures, professional, religious, and national identities.</p><p>Our self-preservation mechanisms inevitably start to preserve these social constructions. Yes, we waste resources, but usually it's safer to avoid changes, rather than playing with the fire of the unknown. However, the world doesn't stand still. Collective identities based on long forgotten goals always lose synchronization with reality. It's just a matter of time.</p><p>This leads us to a choice. Preservation or change. We either keep pushing traditional options, or clarify our goals, discard the orphaned rules, keep the good ones, and fearlessly proceed with evolution.</p><p>What will you choose?</p></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/good-bad-traditional</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/good-bad-traditional</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>philosophy</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Pathfinders</title>
    <description><p>The first rules in the universe, created by the pioneers, the basic intelligent structures, would be made out of chaos. Pure. Impulsive. Meaningless. Skipping a few million years, we design our rules using other rules. They have preceding rules, something that we call a "reason" to exist.</p><p>It doesn't have to be a good reason, of course, but now we see this pattern everywhere. We notice that actions are performed for a reason and things are created or destroyed for a reason.</p><p>Then we learn how to work with transitivity. You may have a distant goal and create something that will lead you to it. That something in the middle will have not only a reason to exist, but a new quality that we may call a "purpose".</p><p>In some sense, purpose exists only within that triangle of transitivity. If you remove any part of it, the purpose vanishes automatically. This is why it's so hard to find it in life. Usually, there are missing parts of the equation.</p><p>Our emotional self-diagnosing system utilizes information on the alignment of incoming data with already existing sequences in memory, in our <a href='/post/internal-world'>pattern-based internal worlds</a>.</p><p>This leads us to that weird feeling of unease when the pattern breaks. It's difficult to process that so many insignificant things around have their purposes and you suddenly don't.</p><p>A substitute can be created. If you set a goal, then you may treat yourself today as a creator with some reason in mind, and yourself tomorrow as someone who will have a purpose. This self-creation, a personal "calling", replaces the missing triangle, fixes the broken pattern, and provides peace of mind.</p><p>But how do you choose a goal? It's not a problem to be solved by pure reasoning, is it? Without any grand purpose, you'll have to make a free choice, one way or another.</p><p>If you prefer to fill the hole in your heart, to get a purpose, you'll have to embrace the chaos once again. We aren't that different from the pioneers. Fire will show you the path, but you have to step into the darkness to dance with shadows.</p><p>Advanced self-preservation mechanisms will vote against that game, poisoning our minds with existential fear of freedom, pushing all of us into the patterns of behavior (10) and (16).</p><p>Some get stuck in there, avoiding changes, collecting fears, accepting guidance and protection, even from imaginary beings. But it's not the only way. There are other patterns to choose from. You can create your own path. Just don't forget the lighter.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/pathfinders</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/pathfinders</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>psychology</category>
        <category>philosophy</category>
        <category>free_will</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Rigged democracy</title>
    <description><p>If we take a group of people and make them vote for a single leader, what <a href='/evolutionary-theory-of-behavior'>pattern of behavior</a> would they choose? Is this election even fair, or is the winner always predetermined?</p><p>Let's be honest. Would you like a lazy customer (11+14) to be the president? I doubt that he would work hard for society. Adaptive victim (9+15) perhaps? Let's ignore problems and cry together! No? Maybe we should try something more proactive? Obsessed gladiator (2+5) is an excellent choice. We haven't seen enough guillotines on the streets recently. No again? Interesting.</p><p>Following your logic, we'll discard helpless conformists (10+16) for being full of fear and incapable of ruling, fools (13) for wasting resources, invisible prisoners (1+7) for bringing uncontrollable aggression, genius philosophers (3+8) for following forbidden desires and provocations...</p><p>Wait, wait, wait. You lead us to a bizarre conclusion. Out of 16 patterns, only three seem to be more or less acceptable to the majority. Artist (6), recidivist (4), and apologetic one (12).</p><p>And they're not equal yet. Artist requires an environment that will ignore him. We can find examples of local governors who create beautiful places to live out of small towns in the middle of nowhere, but the moment we get into big politics with its publicity and pressure, this choice practically disappears.</p><p>This leaves us with two candidates. Recidivist destroys things to protect something. Apologetic one mirrors that, and invests in reconstruction. And they can succeed each other in a cycle.</p><p>Dangerous events happen. People need protection and vote for a recidivist. His precise destruction is welcomed at first, but he can't stop. People get frustrated and choose the opposite. Something bad happens eventually, and history repeats itself.</p><p>Naturally, two mirrored patterns create the same conflict of logic that we see in schizophrenia. Executive organs that try to cheat and use them simultaneously always work awkwardly.</p><p>Since recidivist is the only proactive pattern in the pair, we expect to see more annoying marketing from that side. Have you noticed how these guys on TV constantly talk about protecting you from something that you never saw? It's not a coincidence.</p><p>To put the final nail in the coffin, none of the patterns in the last column of our table, including these two, utilize long-term memory. If you feel like the chosen politicians have a memory of a goldfish, they do. This is how patterns work.</p><p>Democracy. What can I say? Does it really depend on your vote?</p></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/rigged-democracy</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/rigged-democracy</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>politics</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Unresolvable conflict</title>
    <description><p>What exact event is a trigger of schizophrenia? Depression? Mania? Catatonia? It seems like psychiatrists tend to use extremely vague wordings in their answers. Let's make things clear.</p><p>We need to break the main control flow of the system and force it to go against itself by feeding data to it. What vectors of attacks are possible and can lead directly to these diseases?</p><p>Tricky sequences passed to the pattern-recognition modules, equivalents of code injections, make you misinterpret data from your inputs. It's weird, but hardly damages the system.</p><p>Memory has to be updated using new data, which leads to an awkward feeling of cognitive dissonance. It's not a disease.</p><p>In a busy environment, your memory caches can be overwhelmed by information. It's like a DoS attack of sorts. Makes you distracted and unproductive. In some cases, cache overflow can be abused to push unprotected data into the processor, increasing suggestibility so to speak, but it's not a permanent disease.</p><p><a href='/post/compromised'>Hallucinations</a> and dissociative disorders, caused by reading and writing into memory during its hot maintenance, are important issues, but not the ones we're looking for.</p><p>Dangerous environments and related trauma push you towards suitable patterns of behavior. Our system is designed to handle this. It won't break completely. What else can we do?</p><p>There are conflicts of interest. Limited resources force you to evaluate priorities and make hard choices. It's stressful, but it's not enough. We need to orchestrate an unresolvable conflict inside the decision-making unit in order to break it.</p><p>Provide a choice with equally valuable options that'll require a subject to use logically incompatible patterns of behavior of class I, mirrored for schizophrenia, arbitrary for catatonia, proactive or reactive for mania and depression respectively.</p><p>This kind of choice creates hesitation, almost catatonia-like stupor or agitation that can't be resolved by reasoning. We apply serious tension that rips apart two main switches that control the direction of behavior, and the forces aren't "just thoughts", they are real conflicting physical processes.</p><p>Switches won't last forever under such abuse, especially if they're already compromised by bad genes aka wrong assembly instructions, disruptions during early development, or various processes that just wear them over time.</p><p>Unresolvable logical conflict can become the last drop.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/unresolvable-conflict</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/unresolvable-conflict</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>psychology</category>
        <category>schizophrenia</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Field of prey</title>
    <description><p>Take a chimp who just ripped an arm from some small monkey, passed it with a smile to his brother to enjoy a lunch together, and tell him that they became so violent because their mother didn't like them enough.</p><p>They'll laugh at you and suggest that you try a leg. They're designed to be predators! It's natural for them. But if so, at what exact moment of evolution did we get an idea that we're not designed to behave like they do?</p><p>Or is it "not supposed"?</p><p>Do we have to suppress our nature to make some snowflakes feel comfortable? This question isn't only about bloody aggression. There are lots of things to do on that side, but psychology as a field becomes focused on repressing or ignoring proactive predators and supporting reactive behavior, suitable for prey.</p><p>As a therapist, you may not see that bias as a problem. It's understandable. You work with <a href='/post/trauma'>traumatized</a> people. All of your clients happen to use reactive patterns of behavior.</p><p>Your tools and tricks have to work with prey, but not with predators. They'll never go to therapy anyway, unless they end up in some asylum for the criminally insane. Hopeless cases, aren't they? What a shame!</p><p>Average therapists see the same reactive patterns of behavior (9) and (15) all the time, separately or within patterns of class II, and help clients switch to adjacent patterns. At some moment I became bored studying practical cases. It's a constant deja vu. Local circumstances are like ripples on water, but the waves that hit the lighthouse never change.</p><p>This environment creates a tunnel vision of sorts in the heads of professionals. They live in the field of prey.</p><p>Some even start to see reactive patterns of behavior as normal and desirable ones and claim proactive patterns to be traumatized and <a href='/post/relative-irrationality'>irrational</a>. It's a limited picture of the world that can quietly poison the minds of all their clients.</p><p>Psychology is supposed to be a field that studies the psyche as it is, but the more I learn about behavior-related schools and observe therapists, the more it looks like they tend to shape and force some censored understanding instead.</p><p>Your clients don't represent the world in all its diversity. Be careful with generalizations. Convenience is not nature.</p><p>The fox that steals from your farm is not sick.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/field-of-prey</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/field-of-prey</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>psychology</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Selected to be sick</title>
    <description><p>Recently, I witnessed an interesting discussion about natural selection. The vast majority of participants supported an idea that depression provides benefits to our species. We were selected to be able to have it from time to time.</p><p>The main argument was that an organism in depression saves energy and reduces risks by not participating in dangerous endeavors and interactions. It's a simple survival strategy.</p><p>There are bits of evidence that support that story. It seems convincing. However, if we interpret it from the perspective of my work, we may come to a different conclusion.</p><p>Complexity of systems increases with time. Combinations. Mutations. You know the drill. It's a long process. We get our 16 patterns of behavior eventually. We can do various things and can work efficiently in different circumstances.</p><p>Flexibility of behavior may or may not be beneficial on its own, but it becomes extremely important when we build the next levels of complexity. Groups. Societies. Civilization. We need all our patterns of behavior to construct the world we know.</p><p>There is an issue, or course. Sophisticated system of patterns requires switches. Small and fragile. They can be destroyed by force. They can get stuck or start to wobble. This is where we get a variety of malfunctions, depression included.</p><p>Psychiatric diseases are inevitable at our level. We weren't selected to have one disease or another because it's cool to be sick. We just became too complex to avoid them.</p><p>Species with simple designs, with one pattern to follow, if any, would be immune to depression. No switches. No problems. However, their civilization will require symbiotic connections between many species with different default patterns.</p><p>Technically, it should be possible, but these species will have to share their communication protocols and synchronize their long-term goals. It's a tricky task, especially for biological systems that depend on random mutations in their evolution. Chances won't be in their favor.</p><p>I think we should be careful when speculating about natural selection and the benefits of having diseases. It's easy to convince ourselves of something because it sounds good, but completely miss the engineering aspects of that phenomenon.</p><p>It's much more interesting to design different species from scratch and see all the technical limitations. It becomes obvious that sometimes systems are vulnerable by design.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/selected-to-be-sick</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/selected-to-be-sick</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>methodology</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Intuition</title>
    <description><p>Sequences of data are basic building blocks of memory. They may have various functional roles. Let's take a look at some.</p><p>Facts. These are your most standard pieces of information. If a sequence is a fact, then it exists. It's true.</p><p>Associations. They may look differently, depending on your technical design, but their role is to connect other sequences. These are like edges of the graph of memories.</p><p>Rules. These are like instructions for reasoning and behavior, based on one-directional associations. It's your program.</p><p>Patterns. We save them as symbols and build an <a href='/post/internal-world'>internal world</a>. When we combine them with fuzzy transitivity and create complex associations, we get some understanding of reality.</p><p>These roles exist without any languages. Yes, it may sound odd outside of the IT world, but that's the fact. Programs in our computers don't speak, but they work with all these things.</p><p>What happens when we add a language? We add a bunch of facts. Words. We find more patterns for grammar and stuff. We add associations to connect words with our facts and symbols.</p><p>When you walk through your graph of memories, you can grab the words that are connected to your path. Make a sentence. It doesn't have to be grammatically perfect, but you can explain your line of thought to others. But what if your path goes through multiple sequences with no words associated with them?</p><p>Fact can be reproduced as it is. You can draw a picture, make a sound, or whatever your design allows you to do. If your listener has similar experiences, it can be enough to make the right guess. It's not a silver bullet, but it works.</p><p>Associations are easy to explain. Things come together. We connect them. Rules are the same. You can forget why you created some rules, but you can share them with us. If you use transitivity, then just explain everything step by step.</p><p>But what about patterns? If you don't have any words for a symbol or its parts, then you have a problem. It would be practically impossible to explain it. You may share every fact in a symbolic group, but it's highly unlikely that your opponent will find some tricky pattern immediately.</p><p>If you spend some time with data from the same environment, you find a lot of patterns and get a good understanding of it, but there are no words to explain it. Everything works, but you can't share anything. It's like personal magic.</p><p>Intuition.</p></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/intuition</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/intuition</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>memory</category>
        <category>intelligence</category>
    </item>
    <item>
    <title>Internal world</title>
    <description><p>Let's say you have some basic consciousness. You save and extract data from your memory. What's next? How to evolve? Try to mix things. Associate sequences of data if they come together.</p><p>Now compare some sequences. Are they identical? Similar? You don't understand anything at this moment, but you can make a rule. A to B. Once you receive a sequence A, find that rule and proceed to B.</p><p>Do you have any free will in your pockets? Use it. Override your instructions for behavior with new rules. You can create rules and follow them. You got a tiny bit of intelligence. Congratulations! You're a genius bacteria! It's time to <a href='/post/the-magical-number-6'>increase your cache</a> and play with more complex relations.</p><p>Take three sequences. A. B. S. If A = S, and B = S, then A = B. You just learned Euclidean relations. Great. Try to work with parts. If A includes S1 and S2, and B includes S1 and S2, then A = B. We're getting somewhere. Try to compare a lot of sequences. Find a pattern.</p><p>A = B = C = D = E... = S1 + S2 + X.</p><p>What is this? It's a symbol. How do you call it? You don't. You don't speak any languages yet. But you can save it. You can play with sequences of data that exist only in your head, finding patterns in patterns, and creating a symbolic world.</p><p>Patterns and symbols are cool, but you may want to learn fuzzy transitivity as well. If you have a sequence S, it's connected to A, and A to B, then S is connected to B.</p><p>Now you can see a destination of a sequence. Reuse skills with various subjects in a symbolic group. Play with associations. You can build a lot of things, even a fancy conflict-resolving module for your rules, where you wander around the memory graph and find alternative rules for some tricky situation.</p><p>We may be from different species, but we exist in the same environment and have similar sensors. We likely receive similar sequences of data. We find more or less the same patterns and save them as symbols. This is our collective unconscious. By using it, we align our actions even if we don't know each other and don't have any common language.</p><p>Oh, right. We'll need a language. Our internal worlds may be relatively unique, but we associate sequences that come together. One day we'll find a common sequence. A word. An adapter between one of my sequences and one of yours. We can make a conversation now.</p><p>Do you monitor some of your data channels? Yes? So you have a live feed of your... thoughts? You <a href='/post/selfie'>observe</a> sequences of data? Feel symbolic connections? And even say the words of our language somewhere inside?</p><p>Wow!</p><p>It's quite a mind you have!</p></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <link>https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/internal-world</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sfi0zy.github.io/post/internal-world</guid>
    
        <category>evolution</category>
        <category>memory</category>
        <category>intelligence</category>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>